Throughout the history of computers
على امتداد تاريخ الحواسيب
we've been striving to shorten the gap between us
ظللنا نسعى لردم الهوة بيننا
and digital information,
وبين المعلومات الرقمية،
the gap between our physical world
الهوة بين عالمنا الفيزيائي
and the world in the screen
والعالم الموجود على شاشتنا
where our imagination can go wild.
حيث يمكن لخيالنا أن يسرح بعيدا.
And this gap has become shorter,
وهذه الهوة قد صارت أصغر،
shorter, and even shorter,
شيءً فشيءً،
and now this gap is shortened down
وقد تم تقليص هذه الهوة إلى
to less than a millimeter,
أقل من مليمتر واحد،
the thickness of a touch-screen glass,
سمك زجاج شاشات اللمس،
and the power of computing
وقوة الحوسبة
has become accessible to everyone.
قد صارت متوفرة للجميع.
But I wondered, what if there could be no boundary at all?
لكنني أتساءل ما إذا كانت هناك حدود على الإطلاق؟
I started to imagine what this would look like.
بدأت في تخيل ما قد يبدو عليه ذلك.
First, I created this tool
أولا، أنشأت هذه الأداة.
which penetrates into the digital space,
والتي تخترق الفضاء الرقمي،
so when you press it hard on the screen,
بحيث حين تضغط عليها بقوة على الشاشة،
it transfers its physical body into pixels.
تقوم بتحويل جسمها المادي إلى بكسلات.
Designers can materialize their ideas
يستطيع المصممون جعل أفكارهم مادية
directly in 3D,
بشكل ثلاثي الأبعاد مباشرة،
and surgeons can practice on virtual organs
ويستطيع الجراحون التدرب على أعضاء افتراضية
underneath the screen.
تحت الشاشة.
So with this tool, this boundary has been broken.
إذن بهذه الأداة، تم كسر الحواجز.
But our two hands still remain outside the screen.
لكن يدينا الاثنتين لا تزالان خارج الشاشة.
How can you reach inside and interact
كيف يمكنك أن تمدها إلى الداخل وتتفاعل
with the digital information
مع المعلومات الرقمية
using the full dexterity of our hands?
باستخدام المهارات التامة ليديك؟
At Microsoft Applied Sciences,
في مختبر ميكروسوفت للعلوم التطبيقية،
along with my mentor Cati Boulanger,
ومع مرشدتي كاتي بوولنجر،
I redesigned the computer
قمت بإعادة تصميم الحاسوب
and turned a little space above the keyboard
وتحويل فضاء صغير فوق لوحة المفاتيح
into a digital workspace.
إلى فضاء عمل رقمي.
By combining a transparent display and depth cameras
من خلال الجمع بين العرض الشفاف وكاميرات العمق
for sensing your fingers and face,
من أجل استشعار أصابعك ووجهك،
now you can lift up your hands from the keyboard
يمكنك الآن رفع يديك من لوحة المفاتيح
and reach inside this 3D space
وتمدها داخل هذا الفضاء الثلاثي الأبعاد
and grab pixels with your bare hands.
وتلتقط بكسلات بيدك المجردة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Because windows and files have a position in the real space,
ولأن النوافذ والملفات لها موضع في الفضاء الحقيقي،
selecting them is as easy as grabbing a book off your shelf.
اختيارها سيكون بقدر سهولة التقاط كتاب من رفكم.
Then you can flip through this book
ومن ثم يمكنك تصفح هذا الكتاب
while highlighting the lines, words
وأنت تقوم بتعليم السطور والكلمات
on the virtual touch pad below each floating window.
على لوحة اللمس الافتراضية تحت كل نافذة طافية.
Architects can stretch or rotate the models
يمكن للمعماريين أن يقوموا بتمديد أو إدارة النماذج
with their two hands directly.
بأيديهم مباشرة.
So in these examples,
إذن في هذه الأمثلة،
we are reaching into the digital world.
نمد أيدينا إلى العالم الرقمي.
But how about reversing its role
لكن ماذا عن عكس هذا الدور
and having the digital information reach us instead?
وجعل المعلومات الرقمية تصل إلينا بدل ذلك؟
I'm sure many of us have had the experience
أنا متأكد من أن الكثير منا قد خاض هذه التجربة من قبل
of buying and returning items online.
شراء أشياء وإرجاعها عن طريق الانترنت.
But now you don't have to worry about it.
لكن ليس عليك القلق حيال ذلك الآن.
What I got here is an online augmented fitting room.
ما لدينا هنا هو غرفة تجريب ملابس معززة.
This is a view that you get from
تلك هي الرؤية التي تحصلون عليها من
head-mounted or see-through display
أجهزة الرؤية الرأسية أو الشاشات الشفافة
when the system understands the geometry of your body.
حين يستوعب النظام هندسة جسدكم.
Taking this idea further, I started to think,
ولأخذ هذه الفكرة لأبعد من ذلك، بدأت أفكر
instead of just seeing these pixels in our space,
بدل مشاهدة هذه البكسلات في فضائنا فقط،
how can we make it physical
كيف يمكننا جعلها مادية
so that we can touch and feel it?
بحيث يمكننا لمسها والشعور بها؟
What would such a future look like?
كيف سيبدو مستقبل كهذا؟
At MIT Media Lab, along with my advisor Hiroshi Ishii
في مختبر الوسائط بMIT، ومع المشرف على بحثي، هيروشي إيشي،
and my collaborator Rehmi Post,
والمتعاون معنا، ريمي بوست،
we created this one physical pixel.
أنشأنا هذا البكسل المادي الواحد.
Well, in this case, this spherical magnet
حسنا، في هذه الحالة، هذا المغناطيس الكروي
acts like a 3D pixel in our space,
يتصرف كبكسل ثلاثي الأبعاد في فضائنا،
which means that both computers and people
ما يعني أن كلا من الناس والحواسيب
can move this object to anywhere
يستطيعون تحريك هذا الجسم إلى أي مكان
within this little 3D space.
في حدود هذا الفضاء الثلاثي الأبعاد.
What we did was essentially canceling gravity
ما قمنا به باختصار هو إلغاء الجاذبية
and controlling the movement by combining
والتحكم في الحركة من خلال دمج
magnetic levitation and mechanical actuation
الاسترفاع المغناطيسي والدفع الميكانيكي
and sensing technologies.
وتكنولوجيات الاستشعار.
And by digitally programming the object,
ومن خلال برمجة الجسم رقميا،
we are liberating the object from constraints
نقوم بتحرير الجسم من القيود
of time and space, which means that now,
الزمنية والمكانية، ما يعني أنه الآن،
human motions can be recorded and played back
الحركات البشرية يمكن تسجيلها وإعادة تشغيلها
and left permanently in the physical world.
وتركها بشكل دائم في العالم المادي.
So choreography can be taught physically over distance
وبالتالي يمكن تعليم الرقص عن بعد
and Michael Jordan's famous shooting can be replicated
ويمكن إعادة تمثيل رمية مايكل جوردان الشهيرة
over and over as a physical reality.
مرارا وتكرارا كحقيقة مادية.
Students can use this as a tool
يستطيع الطلبة استخدام هذه الأداة
to learn about the complex concepts
لتعلم المبادئ المعقدة
such as planetary motion, physics,
مثل حركة الكواكب والفيزياء
and unlike computer screens or textbooks,
وعلى خلاف شاشات الحواسيب أو الكتب،
this is a real, tangible experience
فإن هذه تجربة ملموسة وحقيقية
that you can touch and feel, and it's very powerful.
يمكنك لمسها والشعور بها، وهي في غاية القوة.
And what's more exciting
والأكثر إثارة للحماس
than just turning what's currently in the computer physical
من مجرد تحويل ما يوجد حاليا في الحاسوب إلى ما هو مادي
is to start imagining how programming the world
هو البدء في تخيل كيف أن برمجة العالم
will alter even our daily physical activities.
ستغير أنشطتنا الفيزيائية اليومية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
As you can see, the digital information
فالمعلومات الرقمية كما ترون،
will not just show us something
لن ترينا فقط شيء
but it will start directly acting upon us
لكنها ستبدأ بالتأثير بشكل مباشر علينا
as a part of our physical surroundings
كجزء من محيطنا المادي
without disconnecting ourselves from our world.
من دون قطع الصلة بيننا وبين العالم من حولنا.
Today, we started by talking about the boundary,
اليوم، بدأنا بالحديث عن الحاجز،
but if we remove this boundary,
لكن إن أزلنا هذا الحاجز،
the only boundary left is our imagination.
الحاجز الوحيد المتبقي هو مخيلتكم.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)